Should you get on testosterone if your
testosterone level is under 400?
>> It depends. Like if you have metabolic
disease and
you are on weight loss drugs or thinking
about it and you're obese, yeah,
potentially testosterone can help you.
Not everybody. See, the thing is it
shouldn't be just based on your level.
It should also be take into account what
are your symptoms and can the
testosterone
help or be estimated to help with those
particular symptoms given your levels.
So I'll give you two examples. So there
are guys that have levels of 400 450 500
and they say oh well you know my sex
drive is lower than it was when I was
20. And they're like 50 or something
like that. And that's their only
concern. Let's say they have perfect
body composition
and I'm going to say, well, I mean, the
testosterone may or may not improve your
sex drive. It may even make it worse.
So, there's a limited benefits. But if
they're obese and they have pre-diabetes
and they need to lose weight, then yes,
it's it's very often it can it can help
or it should be at least uh considered.
I've met [clears throat] guys and I met
a guy recently whose total testosterone
level is like 270 and it's been that way
for a decade. He has like 8% body fat,
no diseases. Um, but he does like cold
plunges. He's like a junkie that he's
like one of those cold junkies that does
like those really ice bath like things
every day. Yeah.
>> And so I think that has something to do
with it because I, for example, I've
encountered other patients with no
symptoms of testosterone deficiency, but
subnormal testosterone levels uh who are
otherwise perfectly healthy labwise,
symptom-wise, body composition wise. So
it's ne, you know, it's never just based
only on your level, which is a lot of
doctors don't even understand that. What
what matters most is can can you be
expected to benefit from it medically,
not what is your level. And there's a
lot of nuance that goes into determining
that. There are even men with low levels
that shouldn't be on testosterone.
Okay? Let's say, you know, you're an
18year-old who doesn't sleep and spends
eight hours in the gym. I've seen tons
of these kids and even in their 20s.
Yeah, I'm in the gym four hours a day.
How much do you sleep? Well, I work 60
hours a week, so I sleep four hours a
night. Your testosterone levels 240.
Should that kid be put on testosterone?
Absolutely not. Absolutely not. Not when
it's strictly your lifestyle and you're
very young, meaning your duration
dependent risk is highest. Um, so yeah,
it's an individualistic thing.
>> Individualistic. Also a general thought
if someone was low on testosterone like
whether it be 250 or 400 and he has no
symptoms at all could he still benefit
from taking testosterone
like for health or bones or mineral
density or something like that?
>> I would say yes. Well, number one, yes,
tes testosterone
has beneficial effects on body
composition in virtually everybody, even
people with so-called normal levels. So,
what happens when you age is aging is
kind of like an inflammatory disease. It
causes you to lose muscle mass.
>> It's called age related sarcopenia and
it causes you to lo to gain fat
including visceral fat. So I think
patients with very low muscle mass and
patients and especially if they also
have um you know high amounts of
visceral fat.
So we see that sometimes there are
non-obese patients with very high
visceral fat. That's a silent killer.
Those are the people that get cancer
that get diabetes. They're called skinny
diabetics. There's an epidemic of skinny
diabetics in in India for example um
right now and those are people with a
lot of visceral fat but technically
their waist circumference is not doesn't
meet the criteria for obesity or their
BMI is not very high um and I do think
those um patients can in many cases
benefit yeah I do and that that's the
part of my practice that's um that I
like kind of specialize in because any
guy who's like 50, obese, and has a
testosterone level of 200. I mean, even
today, a lot of primary care doctors are
not going to say you don't need
testosterone. Some might, but you know,
okay, some might, but but increasingly
many won't. So, I get a lot of the guys
that, oh, my level's 400, my doctor
checked it three times, but my BMI is
like 42 and I'm about to have beriatric
surgery. and you know their their their
disease profile is a mess. So we're
experts at using testosterone in those
patients.
>> Yeah.